Register of the Joaquin Maurin Papers, 1870-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Joaquin Maurin Papers,
1870-1976
77021
Maurin, Joaquin, 1897-1973
31 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 3 envelopes. (13.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, clippings, photographs, and printed matter, relating to communism and socialism in Spain, the Spanish Civil War, and the American Literary Agency.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Nin, Andres, 1892-1937.; American Literary Agency.; Partido obrero de unificacion marxista.; Communism.; Communism--Spain.; Fascism--Spain.; Labor movement--Spain.; Socialism--Spain.; Spain.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain--Politics and government--20th century.
Biographical Note and Chronology of Related Events
1896, January 13 Born in Bonansa, Huesca (Spain), of Aragon mother and Catalan father
1914-1918 Teacher of geography and history at Lerida high-school Member of "Juventud Republicana", Lerida Writer for El Ideal, the daily mouthpiece of "Juventud Republicana"
1919, December 2nd Congress of the "Confederacion Nacional del Trabajo" (C.N.T.) in Madrid during which it decided to affiliate itself with the Communist International
1919-mid 1920 Stationed in Madrid during his tour of duty in the Spanish army
mid 1920 Joined the C.N.T.
fall 1920-1921 Secretary of the "Confederacion Provincial del Trabajo", Lerida Member of the regional committee of Catalonia of the C.N.T., representing the province of Lerida
1920-1922 Editor of Lucha Social, Lerida, a trade-unionist weekly founded by Pedro Bonet in 1919
1921, May Left with Andres Nin, Arlandis and Ibanez for Moscow
1921, June-August Delegate of the C.N.T. to the 3rd Congress of the Communist International and to the Founding Congress of the Red International of Labor Unions (Profintern)
1921, October National plenum of the C.N.T. in Lerida at which the report of the delegation, written by Maurin, was unanimously approved
1921, October-end of February 1922 Provisional secretary of the executive committee of the C.N.T.
1922, June National conference of the C.N.T. in Saragossa at which it rejected the Communist International and the Profintern (triumph of the anarcho-sindicalist position within the C.N.T.)
1922, December Co-founder at a meeting in Bilbao of the "Comites Sindicalistas Revolucionarios" (C.S.R.), minority within the C.N.T., close to the "Partido Comunista de Espana" (P.C.E.) and which wanted the C.N.T. to reaffiliate itself with the Communist International
1922, December 21-December 1924 Founder and editor of La Batalla, Barcelona, a trade-unionist communist weekly, mouthpiece of the C.S.R., around which gathered a group of Catalan communists and which was subsequently incorporated into the P.C.E. in 1924
1923 Left the C.N.T.
1924, May Author, L'anarcho-syndicalisme en Espagne (Anarcho-sindicalism in Spain), Paris, Librairie du Travail; 47 p.
1924, June-July Delegate to the 3rd Congress of the Profintern sent by the executive committee of the C.S.R.
1924, mid November Plenum of the regional federations of the P.C.E. in Madrid at which Maurin and his group (the "Federacion Comunista Catalano-Balear", F.C.C.B.) criticized the policy of the executive committee, forcing it to resign
1925, January 12 Arrested as he was coming out of the Ateneo of Barcelona
1925, January 12-October 4, 1927 Political prisoner, first in the prison "Modelo" in Barcelona, then in the fortress of Montjuich, then again in Barcelona
1926, November 23 Acquitted, but not released immediately
1927, November-June 1930 Resided in Neuilly s/Seine (Paris) Worked for Le Monde Correspondent for Tass and Izvestia on Spanish issues
1927, November 26 Married Jeanne Lifchitz (sister of Boris Souvarine)
1928, March-May Went to Moscow to justify his position to the Control Commission of the Communist International; whitewashed and offered to be member of the executive committee of the P.C.E.: refused
1928, December 22 Birth of son Mario in Paris
1929, August 3rd Congress of the P.C.E. in Paris. The F.C.C.B. had to send its proposals, Maurin and Bonet not having been allowed to attend as delegates
1930, June Returned to Spain after the fall of Primo de Rivera
1930, Summer So-called Conference of Pamplona of the P.C.E. to which the F.C.C.B. was not invited Maurin expelled from the party. The F.C.C.B. sided with him and was also expelled, and started seeking contacts with the "Partit Comunista Catala" that Jordi Arquer and other members of the F.C.C.B. founded in the years 1928-1929, refusing to follow the discipline of the Communist International any longer
1930, October 24 Author, Los Hombres de la Dictadura (The men of the dictatorship), Madrid, Cenit; 241 p.
1931, March 1 1st Congress of the F.C.C.B. at Tarrasa. Incorporated the "Partit Comunista Catala" which had agreed to the fusion at its congress in the beginning of November 1930 Founded the "Bloque Obrero y Campesino" (B.O.C.) as a rallying platform and framework for communist sympathisers and as a propaganda organization. The F.C.C.B., in effect, was converted into being the administrator of the B.O.C. Maurin was secretary-general
1931, April 12 The B.O.C. participated in the municipal elections which brought about the end of the monarchy and the proclamation of the Republic on April 14
1931, June Visited by a delegation of the Communist International which wanted the B.O.C. to be incorporated into the P.C.E.; Maurin refused and was expelled from the Communist International in July
1932, January 25 Author, La Revolucion Espanola. De la Monarquia Absoluta a la Revolucion Socialista (The Spanish revolution. From absolute monarchy to the socialist revolution), Madrid, Cenit; 196 p.
1932, April 4 2nd Congress of the F.C.C.B. in Barcelona. Changed its name to "Federacion Comunista Iberica" (F.C.I.)
1933, February Working classes conference convened by the B.O.C. in Barcelona
1933, March The B.O.C. suggested the formation of the "Alianza Obrera Antifascista" which organized the October 1934 uprising
1933, end of June 1st Congress of the F.C.I.
1934, April 2nd Congress of the F.C.I.
1935, April Author, Hacia la Segunda Revolucion (Until the second revolution), Barcelona, Alfa; 253 p. Translated into French in 1935 and published in Paris by Rieder under the title Revolution et Contre-revolution en Espagne; 367 p. Reedited in Spanish in 1966 and published in Paris by Ruedo Iberico under the title Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana (Revolution and counter-revolution in Spain); 289 p.
1935, September Founded the "Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista" (P.O.U.M.) through the fusion of the B.O.C. and the "Izquierda Comunista" that Nin founded in 1932
1936, February Elected Deputy to the Cortes for the city of Barcelona under the "Front d'Esquerres", the Republican coalition of Catalonia, in which he was politically active since the end of 1935
1936, July Wife and son left for Paris Found himself in insurgent territory (Bisquaye, Galicia) at the outbreak of the civil war. Hid under false names
1936, September 3 Arrested. Detained in Panticosa, Huesca, and then in the provincial prison of Jaca, Huesca, under the name of Joaquin Julio Ferrer
1936, September Various newspapers announced his capture and execution
1937, early September Released. Tried to reach France
1937, September 6 Recognized at the border. Arrested under his real name and transferred to Saragossa
1937, October 8 Brother Manuel died in the prison "Modelo" in Barcelona
1937-May 1942 In solitary confinement in the provincial prison of Salamanca
1941, August 30 Wife and son arrived in New York (American citizens in April 1953)
1942, May-November Provincial prison of Barcelona
1942, November-March 1944 Central prison of Burgos Wrote draft of En las Prisiones de Franco (In the prisons of Franco) under the title of "Los Siete Circulos"
1944, March-October 1946 Provincial prison of Barcelona
1944, August 19 His case came up for trial; sentenced to 30 years
1946, October 1 Paroled under an amnesty for some political prisoners, but confined to Madrid where he worked as a translator for Jose Janes Publications
1947, July 4 Was given a passport to visit his family in New York, provided he returned to Spain. Left for Neuilly s/Seine
1947, September 30 American embassy in Paris granted him a temporary visitor's visa
1947, October 16 Arrived in New York (his visa was extended twice, the second time until April 16, 1949)
1947 Held a position with Dana Perfumes of Buenos Aires, which wanted him to undergo a 6-months training period in New York
1948, end of February Injured his back: immobilized for a few months and incapacitated for a year and a half. Unable to return to Spain, he thus forfeited his conditional liberty
1948, March-March 1950 Commercial representative in the U.S. of the Spanish firm PRADESA
1949, July Founded the American Literary Agency (A.L.A.), a newspaper agency which distributed articles written by him and others to some 35 Central and Latin American newspapers
1949, September-July 1952 Commercial representative in the U.S. of the Spanish firm Jose Collado Herrero
1951, January-April 1954 Chief writer for the Boletin de Informac on de Dana, New York
1953 The F.B.I. asked him to leave the country
1954, April September 1957 Press attache to the Costa Rican delegation to the United Nations in New York
1961, April 24 American citizen
1973, November 12 Died in New York
1974, May 5 Author, En Las Prisiones de Franco (In the prisons of Franco), Mexico, B. Costa-Amic; 210 p.
For further information, see the correspondence file for the following correspondents, to which Maurin gave answers to specific reference questions about his past activities and Spanish politics of the 1920s and 1930s: Arquer, Jordi; Bonamusa Gaspa, Francisco; Cardona, Jose Manuel; Connelly Ullman, Joan; Kairis, Robert A.; Meaker, Gerald H.; Pages, Pedro (Victor Alba); Payne, Stanley; Portela, Luis; Thomas, Hugh; Wolfe, Bertram and Ella
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1896-1974. (Box 1-2.)
  Arranged chronologically.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1973. (Box 2-11.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1918-1973. (Box 12-19.)
  Arranged alphabetically by title within two chronological subdivisions, before and after 1948.
- AMERICAN LITERARY AGENCY, 1949-1973. (Box 19-24.)
  Material related to the newspaper agency that Maurin founded in July 1949 and which distributed articles written by him and others to some thirty-five Central and Latin American newspapers. General office correspondence, arranged chronologically, and articles written by Maurin for the Agency, arranged chronologically under the various pen names he used
- SUBJECT FILE, 1870-1973. (Box 25-29.)
  Correspondence, printed matter, minutes, newsletters, reports, arranged alphabetically by topic
- NEWSPAPERS, 1919-1976. (Box 30-31.)
  Arranged alphabetically by title
- MEMORABILIA, 1950-1952. (Box 32 on shelf.)
  Two oversize scrapbooks.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1920s-1970s. (Box 10. A-V.)
  See photo card catalog
- Appendix to register
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1896-1974
  - Articles on Joaquin Maurin (hereafter Maurin) (Box 1)
  - Biographical data
  - Pre-1936 identification documents (passports, certificates, passes, etc.)
  - Pre-1936 miscellaneous papers
  - Imprisonment, 1925-1927
  - Letters of support to Maurin in his controversy with Gabriel Leon Trilla, 1928
  - Deputy to the Cortes, 1936. See also SUBJECT FILE, Spain, Catalonia, Elections
  - Envelopes of letters sent to his wife while in prison, 1943-1944
  - Judgement, 1944, and conditional release, 1946
  - Job applications, 1949
  - Visa and naturalization process, 1947-1961
    - Biographical data submitted
    - Birth certificate, good conduct certificate and finger prints
    - Correspondence
      - of Jeanne Maurin (hereafter JM) with various people, 1942-1957
      - of JM and Maurin with Max Blecher, Attorney, 1948-1957
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1951
    - Documents submitted and affidavits of various people, 1947-1954
    - Miscellaneous notes by Maurin
    - State Department and Justice Department; Immigration and Naturalization Service 1941-1954
      - General (including articles on immigration laws)
      - Articles written by Maurin submitted to the State Department
    - Citizenship, 1961
  - Post-1946 Spanish and American passports
  - Member of the Costa Rican delegation to the United Nations, N.Y., 1954-1957
  - United Nations press cards
  - Invitations from various United Nations delegations
  - Membership cards to various societies
  - Vaccination certificates (Box 2)
  - Hospital bills
  - Post-1947 miscellaneous papers
  - obituaries, eulogies, tributes, 1973
  - Condolences sent to JM, 1973-1974
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1915-1973
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
    - Pre-1936
    - Post-1947
    - Anne, 1949
    - Gabriel, 1965-1967
    - Horacio, 1948
    - Maria, 1962
    - Poeta, 1952-1954
    - Rafael, 1959-1964
  - Abril, Francisco, 1962
  - Abril, Xavier, 1931
  - Acadia Company, Inc., N.Y., 1949. See also Collado Herrero, Jose
  - Adroher, Enrique (Gironella), 1947-1949. See also SUBJECT FILE, Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista
  - Agrupacion Cultural de la Pena, Mieres (Diego Santamaria, Secretary), 1932
  - Aguade i Miro, Jaume, 1929-1930
  - Aguado-Andreut, Salvador and Claridad Olalquiaga, 1948-1972. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Aguilar, S.A., Madrid, 1954-1968
  - Aguirre, Jose Antonio. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - Aguirre y Cardenas. Juan, 1947-1948
  - Alba, Victor. See Pages, Pedro
  - Alberich. Manuel, 1950-1963
  - Albertini, Georges, 1961-1964
  - Alberto Erro, Carlos. See SUBJECT FILE Hungary
  - Alberto Sanchez, Luis. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Aldecoa, Ignacio, 1960-1961
  - Alexander, Robert J., 1952-1960
  - Alfarache, Progreso A. (CNT, Mexico), 1960-1963
  - Alliluyeva, Svetlana, 1968
  - Alloza, Fernando, 1970
  - Alsina, Jean, 1950
  - Angel Queredo, Miguel. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Angelopoulos, Angelos, 1962
  - Anllo, Juan, 1967
  - Antoine Chiris Company Inc., N.Y., 1950. See also Collado Herrero, Jose
  - Apolo, Barcelona, 1932
  - Araquistain, Luis (Leviatan and Espana, Madrid), 1928-1959
  - Araquistain, Ramon -son of Luis Araquistain-, 1959-1970
  - Arciniega, Rosa. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Arciniegas, Aurora -daughter of German Arciniegas?-, 1964
  - Arciniegas, Gabriela -daughter of German Arciniegas?-, 1973
  - Arciniegas, German, 1972-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Obituaries
  - Arco Alvarez, Jose Luis del (Lainz y Compania, Havana, Cuba), n.d.
  - Arendt, Hannah. See Spanish Refugee Aid, Inc., N.Y.
  - Argente, Baldomero, 1952-1965. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - Arino, Enrique, 1952
  - Arquer, Jordi. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin and Condolences sent to JM; SUBJECT FILE, Partido Obrero de Unification Marxista and Union Socialista Espanola (Box 3)
    - 1947-1957
    - 1958-1973
  - Ascoli, Max (The Reporter, N.Y.), 1951
  - Asensio, Jose (U.S. Representative of the Spanish Government in exile), 1950-1960
  - Asturias, Miguel Angel and Blanca de Asturias de Mora y Araujo, 1970-1974
  - Ateneo Popular de Mieres, Asturias (Luis Santiago Alvarez, Secretary), 1931-1932
  - Aub, Max, 1963
  - Ayma i Ayala, Jaume, 1963-1964
  - Balius, Jaime, 1958. See also Ruiz, Pablo
  - Ballester-Gozalvo, Jose, 1964
  - Baraibar, Carlos de (Claridad, Madrid), 1935. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Barrieiro, Dr. y Senora, 1963-1964
  - Barrett, Edward W., 1956
  - Barrull, Jaume, 1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Barton, Paul. See Veltrusky, Jiri
  - Basque Delegation, N.Y., 1950
  - La Batalla, Paris, 1950
  - Benedict, Edward E., 1951
  - Benitez, Jaime, 1958-1962. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Bentata, J., 1962. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Berch, Victor A. (Brandeis University, Special Collections, Waltham, Mass.), 1969
  - Berghof, Erich, 1952-1953
  - Berle, Adolf A., 1961
  - Bernard, L. L., 1931
  - Bevan, Aneurin, 1958
  - Blanc, Jorge, 1954
  - Blanc Gaillard de la Roche, Juan -father of Jorge Blanc-, 1949
  - Blecher, Jr., Max, 1960. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Correspondence with Max Blecher
  - Bolloten, Burnett, 1954-1955
  - Bolloten, Gladys Elvie, 1954-1963
  - Bonamusa Gaspa, Francisco, 1931-1972
  - Bondy, Francois, 1953-1957. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - Bonet, Pedro, 1947-1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin
  - Borges, Alberto, 1959-1960
  - Bosh, Juan, 1961-1963. See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, Course on political ideologies given at the Institute of Political Education in San Jose, Costa Rica
  - Bowers, Claude C., 1954
  - Breguelo, Antonio. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Brockway, Fenner, 1947-1948. See also Independent Labour Party
  - Broue, Pierre, 1972
  - Bruguera, Antonio, 1959-1973
  - Bullejos Sanchez, Jose, 1959-1960
  - Burgos, Carmen de, 1931
  - Calamandrei, Mauro, 1966
  - Campalans, Rafael, 1932
  - Campana de Watts, Luz, 1973
  - Camus, Albert, 1959
  - Canas, Alberto F., 1955-1973
  - Cano, Rafael del (Ateneo Cientifico, Literario y Artistico, Madrid), 1931
  - Cantinflas. See Moreno, Mario
  - Capdevilla, Arturo. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Capdevilla, Jose, 1948-1960
  - Capella, See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Carballo, Jose F., 1958-1963
  - Carbo, Sergio, 1960
  - Carcagente, Agustin, 1972
  - Cardona, Jose Manuel, 1962-1963
  - Carillo, Santiago, 1935
  - Carod, Saturnino -husband of Adoracion Lahoz-, 1951-1959
  - Carpio, Campio, 1963
  - Carrion, Benjamin, 1955-1960. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary (Box 4)
  - Casajuana, Isidro, 1949-1950
  - Casals, Pablo, 1950-1960
  - Casanovas, Juan, 1928-1929. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to JM
  - Casona, Alejandro. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Castanon de la Pena, Jose Manuel, 1958
  - Castells Vinyals, Jose, 1948-1950
  - Castillo, Othon, 1962-1973
  - Castro, Americo, 1963
  - Cenit S.A., Madrid, 1930-1935
  - Chandler, Tertius, 1955
  - Chaplin, Charlie, 1950
  - Chwat, Paul, 1964
  - Clappier, Louis, 1948-1949
  - Claraso, Noel, 1967
  - Colberg, Severo E. See SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, "Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en la Rusia Sovietica", series of three speeches given at the Graduate School of Public Administration, San Juan, Puerto Rico
  - Collado Herrero, Jose, 1949-1952
  - Collinet, Marcel, 1949
  - Colome, (Comite Departemental de Paris-Seine du P.O.U.M.), 1959
  - Comas, Pere, 1928-1929
  - Comision Coordinadora de la Campana Mundial de Prensa por la Libertad de Espana, Mexico, 1962
  - Communist International
    - Executive Committee, 1928
    - Secretariat, Jules Humbert-Droz, 1928 (including the International Control Commission)
    - Roman Secretariat, 1930
  - Companys, Luis, 1920-1921. See also SUBJECT FILE, Maurin, Jeanne, Correspondence
  - Comunidad Iberica, Mexico, 1966
  - Conference sur la Guerre Politique des Soviets (Rome, Nov. 18-22, 1961), 1961-1962. Correspondence with various participants
  - Connelly Ullman, Joan, 1963. See also SUBJECT FILE, Spain, Anticlericalism
  - Convencion de Republicanos Espanoles de la Argentina, 1973
  - Cortes, Joaquin (CNT, Mexico), 1950-1961
  - Costa Amic, Bartolome, 1948-1960
  - Cuadernos (published by the Congress for Cultural Freedom, Paris), 1953-1963
  - Cuito, Amadeu, 1966
  - Dali, Salvador, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
  - Dana, Doris, 1956
  - Dana Perfumes, Buenos Aires and New York, 1947-1951. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Correspondence, Miscellaneous
  - Darlee, Irina M., 1965
  - Davidson, Jacques, n.d.
  - Deambrosis-Martins, Carlos, 1964 (writing to Stanley Ross, in charge of ALA)
  - Deering-Milliken Export Corporation, N.Y., 1949. See also Collado Herrero, Jose
  - Diego Perez, Ismael, 1957-1958
  - Dolevsky, (Tass, Moscow), 1930
  - Domingo, Marcelino, 1928-1930
  - Dos Passos, John. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Ducach, Teodoro, 1959-1965
  - Dundee Mills Inc., Georgia, 1949. See also Collado Herrero, Jose
  - Dunois, Amedee, 1934
  - Eastman, Max, 1931-1947. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Correspondence of JM and Documents submitted
  - Editors Press Service, Inc., N.Y., 1969-1970
  - Einstein, Albert, 1950
  - Escobal, Patricia P., 1968
  - Escobal, Pedro. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Escudero, Vicente, 1955
  - Espana Libre, Toulouse. See Gonzalez Malo, Jesus and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, "Hombres e Historia"
  - Espla, Carlos, 1928-1966
  - Est-Ouest, Paris. See Guibert, Yves
  - Estenger, Rafael, 1970
  - Estevez, Eulogio, 1930
  - Facio, Gonzalo J., 1953
  - Faulkner, William. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Federacion Local de Sindicatos y Sociedades Obreras, La Fuelguera, Asturias, 1932
  - Federacion Local de Sociedades y Sindicatos Obreros (A.I.T.-C.N.T.), Gijon, 1932
  - Feldman, Harry M., 1956
  - Fernandez Gutierrez, Julian, 1967
  - Ferrandiz, D. F., 1950
  - Ferrater Mora, Jose, 1954-1973. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Ferrer, Miguel, 1929-1930. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Letters of support to Maurin
  - Figueres, Jose
    - 1951-1961
    - 1962-1971
  - Fillat, Alvaro, 1951-1952
  - Fisher, Ruth, 1951-1955
  - Florit, Eugenio, 1971
  - Frank, Waldo, 1954-1964. See also SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Galiana, Gregorio R., 1957
  - Galindez, Jesus de, 1954
  - Gallegos, Romulo. See SUBJECT FILE, Hungary
  - Galvez, Benigna -wife of Manolo Villar-, 1952-1957
  - Galvis Ramirez, Alejandro (Vanguardia Liberal, Colombia), 1970
  - Garcia, Manuel M., 1952
  - Garcia, Pilar (Pili), 1947-1952
  - Garcia Lamola, Pere, 1973. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Garcia Lopez, A., 1960
  - Garcia Lorca, Francisco, 1949-1963. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Garcia Lorca de los Rios, Laura -wife of Francisco Garcia Lorca- (for the Hispanic Institute in the United States, Columbia University), 1953-1967
  - Garcia Pascal, Jose R., 1963-1966
  - Garcia Trevino, Rodrigo (Cuadernos, Mexico), 1955-1959
  - Garcitoral, Alicio, 1957
  - Garrabou, Juan, 1959
  - Geigel-Polanco, Vicente, 1954
  - Gelada, Francisco, 1972-1973
  - General Motors Corporation, N.Y., 1948-1950
  - Gillette, Alberto, 1966
  - Gironella. See Adroher, Enrique
  - Gispert, Maria, 1965. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Condolences sent to JM
  - Givaudan-Delawanna, Inc., 1950
  - Godas i Vila, Frederic, 1948-1957 (Box 6)
  - Godson, Roy, 1966
  - Gomez de la Serna, Ramon, 1956-1962
  - Gondi, Ovidio, 1951-1972. See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and naturalization process, Documents submitted
  - Gonzalez, Bonifacio, 1948-1951
  - Gonzalez, Luis, 1953
  - Gonzalez Feo, Mario, 1960-1966
  - Gonzalez Lopez, Emilio. See Tierno Galvan, Enrique
  - Gonzalez Malo, Jesus, 1957-1967
  - Gonzalez Muela, Joaquin, 1973
  - Gordon, Richard A., 1963-1968
  - Gordon Ordas, Felix, 1957-1959
  - Gorkin, Julian, 1929-1973. See also Cuadernos and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Correspondence of JM and SUBJECT FILE, Hungary and Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista
  - Granell, Eugenio F., 1968
  - Granier. See l'Opinio